{"Topic": "Climate", "Subject": "General Knowledge", "Data": [{"Question": "The main cause of global climatic change is", "op1": "Increase in the content of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere", "op2": "Emissions of industrial gases", "op3": "Adding of dust", "op4": "Changes in plant cover", "Answer": 1}, {"Question": "If there is no carbon dioxide in the earth\u2019s atmosphere, the temperature of earth\u2019s surface would be", "op1": "Dependent on the amount of oxygen in the atmosphere", "op2": "Higher than the present", "op3": "Less than the present", "op4": "The same", "Answer": 3}, {"Question": "High pressure sub-tropical calm belts known as \u2018Horse Latitudes\u2019 lie between", "op1": "0\u00b0 and 10\u00b0", "op2": "15\u00b0 and 25\u00b0", "op3": "20\u00b0 and 25\u00b0", "op4": "30\u00b0 and 35\u00b0", "Answer": 4}, {"Question": "Which from the following can cause a tsunami?", "op1": "Volcano", "op2": "Avalanche", "op3": "Tornado", "op4": "Earthquake", "Answer": 4}, {"Question": "The direction to which wind blows is known as -", "op1": "Windward", "op2": "Leeward", "op3": "Eleaving side", "op4": "None of these", "Answer": 2}, {"Question": "Consider the following statements :", "op1": "1 only", "op2": "2 only", "op3": "Both 1 and 2", "op4": "Neither 1 nor 2", "Answer": 1}, {"Question": "ich of the statements given above is/are correct?", "op1": "Cirrocumulus", "op2": "Cirrostratus", "op3": "Altocumulus", "op4": "Nimbostratus", "Answer": 4}, {"Question": "Which one of the following is a low cloud?", "op1": "Equatorial low pressure belt", "op2": "Sub-tropical high pressure belt", "op3": "Between 10\u00b0  to 23\u00bd\u00b0 North and South Latitudes", "op4": "Sub-polar low pressure belt", "Answer": 1}, {"Question": "Which region of the Earth\u2019s surface is called doldrums?", "op1": "North Atlantic Ocean  : Canaries current", "op2": "Eastern Pacific Ocean  : Kuroshio current", "op3": "South Atlantic Ocean  : Falkland current", "op4": "Indian Ocean  : Agulhas current", "Answer": 2}, {"Question": "Which one of the following pairs of oceans and currents is not correctly matched?", "op1": "A distinct wet and dry season with annual range of temperature between 3\u00b0 C \u2013 8\u00b0 C.", "op2": "Broad-leaf evergreen forests and grasses", "op3": "Uniformly high temperature throughout the year", "op4": "No spatial variation in mean annual rainfall", "Answer": 3}, {"Question": "Savanna natural region is characterized by which one of the following?", "op1": "Europe", "op2": "Asia", "op3": "Africa", "op4": "North America", "Answer": 3}, {"Question": "Name the continent where \u2018Tundra\u2019 type of climate is not found", "op1": "Increases", "op2": "Decreases", "op3": "Remains constant", "op4": "Fluctuates", "Answer": 2}, {"Question": "If the temperature of a place increases suddenly the relative humidity", "op1": "Monsoon", "op2": "Trade wind", "op3": "Land and sea breezes", "op4": "Chinook", "Answer": 2}, {"Question": "Which one of the following is the example of planetary winds?", "op1": "water in the liquid state changes to vapour", "op2": "the dew begins to evaporate", "op3": "water vapour condenses to a liquid", "op4": "hailstones are formed", "Answer": 3}, {"Question": "The dew point is the temperature at which -", "op1": "Nitrous oxide", "op2": "Ozone", "op3": "Sulphur dioxide", "op4": "Carbon dioxide"}, {"Question": "Threat of global warming is increasing due to increasing concentration of", "op1": "A sea storm", "op2": "A warm ocean current", "op3": "A tropical disturbance", "op4": "Another name of typhoon", "Answer": 4}, {"Question": "EI Nino is", "op1": "Formation of day and night", "op2": "Deflection of winds and currents", "op3": "Change of seasons", "op4": "Differences in longitude and time", "Answer": 2}, {"Question": "The earth revolves round the sun. This causes :", "op1": "A - 2; B - 3; C - 1; D - 4", "op2": "A - 2; B - 1; C - 4; D - 3", "op3": "A - 4; B - 1; C - 3; D - 2", "op4": "A - 4; B - 3; C - 1; D - 2", "Answer": 3}, {"Question": "Match List-I with List-II and select the correct answer using the code given below the Lists:"}, {"Question": "Monsoon is caused by", "op1": "Impact of summer temperatures on the seas.", "op2": "Movement of clouds", "op3": "Seasonal reversal of winds", "op4": "Rise in temperature", "Answer": 1}, {"Question": "Consider the following statements :", "op1": "1 only", "op2": "2 only", "op3": "Both 1 and 2", "op4": "Neither 1 nor 2", "Answer": 4}, {"Question": "ch of the statements given above is/are correct?", "op1": "It becomes very hard", "op2": "It reflects most of the heat from the sun", "op3": "It has a low specific heat capacity", "op4": "It has a high latent heat of fusion", "Answer": 2}, {"Question": "The snow on the mountains does NOT melt all at once when it is heated by the sun because", "op1": "of easterly trade winds", "op2": "cold ocean currents flow along the western coasts", "op3": "of the effect of both the off shore easterly trade winds and cold ocean currents", "op4": "the rate of evaporation is greater along the western margin areas", "Answer": 4}, {"Question": "Extensive deserts occur in the western tropical regions of continents because -", "op1": "The rotation of earth", "op2": "The earth\u2019s revolution around the sun", "op3": "The earth\u2019s axis is inclined by 66\u00bd\u00b0", "op4": "Combined effect of (b) and (c) above", "Answer": 1}, {"Question": "Seasons occur because :", "op1": "1013 mb", "op2": "1060 mb", "op3": "960 mb", "op4": "990 mb", "Answer": 3}, {"Question": "The standard sea level in millibars is", "op1": "Iceberg", "op2": "Glacier", "op3": "Avalanche", "op4": "Typhoon", "Answer": 2}, {"Question": "A huge mass of snow moving slowly down the valley and slopes of mountains till it melts after passing the snow line is called :", "op1": "contour lines showing equal amount of sunshine", "op2": "lines on a map joining places which have the same mean temperature", "op3": "contour lines of equal rainfall", "op4": "contour lines of equal air pressure", "Answer": 2}, {"Question": "Isotherms are :", "op1": "A very high pressure centre", "op2": "A very low pressure centre", "op3": "A very high ocean wave", "op4": "A planetary wind", "Answer": 3}, {"Question": "What is a \u2018tornado\u2019?", "op1": "1 only", "op2": "2 only", "op3": "Both 1 and 2", "op4": "Neither 1 nor 2", "Answer": 2}, {"Question": "Consider the following statements:", "op1": "insolation", "op2": "albedo", "op3": "irradiation", "op4": "heat loss", "Answer": 3}, {"Question": "ch of the statements given above is/are correct?", "op1": "trade wind deserts", "op2": "subtropical deserts", "op3": "rainshadow deserts", "op4": "monsoon deserts"}, {"Question": "The fraction of solar energy reflected from Earth into space is known as"}]}